<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../shared.ent" >
%myents;
]>

<chapter id="intro" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section>
    <title>What is MIND ?</title>

    <para>MIND is an implementation of the Fractal component model for the
    development of embedded softwares.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Few words about Fractal</title>

    <para>Fractal is a modular and extensible component model that can be used
    with various programming languages to design, implement, deploy and
    reconfigure various systems and applications, from operating systems to
    middleware platforms and to graphical user interfaces.</para>

    <para>The Fractal component model heavily uses the <emphasis
    role="bold">separation of concerns</emphasis> design principle. The idea
    of this principle is to separate into distinct pieces of code or runtime
    entities the various <emphasis>concerns or aspects</emphasis> of an
    application: implementing the service provided by the application, but
    also making the application configurable, secure, available, ... In
    particular, the Fractal component model uses three specific cases of the
    separation of concerns principle: namely <emphasis>separation of interface
    and implementation</emphasis>, <emphasis>component oriented
    programming</emphasis>, and <emphasis>inversion of control</emphasis>. The
    first pattern, also called the bridge pattern, corresponds to the
    separation of the design and implementation concerns. The second pattern
    corresponds to the separation of the implementation concern into several
    composable, smaller concerns, implemented in well separated entities
    called components. The last pattern corresponds to the separation of the
    functional and configuration concerns: instead of finding and configuring
    themselves the components and resources they need, Fractal components are
    configured and deployed by an external, separated entity.</para>

    <para>For further details, refer to Fractal web site: <ulink
    url="http://fractal.ow2.org/documentation.html"/></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>MIND tool-chain content</title>

    <para>MIND is a modular and extensible architecture compilation tool-chain
    that can be used to compile component-based applications from their
    architectural descriptions (ADL files).</para>

    <para>An integrated development environment based on Eclipse is also
    proposed but not in the scope of this document.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
