<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
  "../dtd/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../shared.ent" >
%myents;
]>
<chapter id="intro">
  <title>
      Introduction
  </title>
  <para>
  &productName; is an extensible source-to-source compilation toolset.
  It is meant to translate component-based programs written in C, whose 
  structure is captured using an Architecture and Interface Description Language
  (ADL and IDL) to pure C code. It also manages the compilation of the output C
  code for various target platforms. 
  </para>
  <para>
  The major feature of &productName; is its ability to be extended to support
  new concepts which are required for a specific domain of application. This can
  be done either by adding annotation to the extensible ADL of &productName;, or
  by adding new input languages which are supported by the toolset.
  </para>
  <para>
  The main challenge of such extensible compilation toolsets is the inflation of
  concepts that are captured in the input language and/or the number of different 
  target platforms to be supported. &productName; deals with this challenge using
  an extremely modular architecture that is integrated using a flexible plugin 
  framework. This architecture allows any external user to develop plugins for 
  &productName; in order to support new concepts in the input language, to extend
  the kind of verifications and code enhancements that are already provided or 
  to re-target
  the generated output code for optimization or other purposes.
  </para>
  
  <section>
  <title> General overview</title>
  
  <para>
  &productName; is written in Java leveraging on the <ulink url="&fractalADLDoc;">FractalADL</ulink>
      framework. So the &productName;. It is composed of various Maven modules. 
  </para>
  <para>
    The summary of these modules is as follows:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      <application>adl-parser</application> defines the grammar of the &productName;
      ADL language.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><application>idl-parser</application> defines the &productName;
        IDL language.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      	<application>common-frontend</application> contains the common components 
      	of the compiler frontend. 
      </para>
      </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	  <para>
	  <application>annotations</application> contains the implementation of the
	  extensible annotation mechanism which is supported by the &productName;
	  ADL language.
	  </para>
	  </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      <application>adl-frontend and idl-frontend</application> contain the components that transforms
      the ADL and IDL syntex trees to an extensible semantic tree which can be used for various purposes,
      such as verification and code generation.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      <application>common-backend</application> contain the main components
      which are used for generating the output code. 
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><application>adl-backend and idl-backend</application> contain 
        the code generators that translate the input ADL and IDL semantic trees
        into C code.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><application>cpl-preproc</application>  implements a custom
        C pre-processor which allows to do some analysis on the input implementation files
        which are written in C.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><application>fractal-runtime</application>  provides 
        a minimal runtime required by fractal components written using the 
        &productName; toolset.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <application>mindc</application> : The integration module that contains the main class
          implementing the the <command>mindc</command> command line interface.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><application>plugin</application> module contains the core plugin system
        which is used to host plugins that are developed by third party users.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
