<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../dtd/minddoc.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "../shared.ent" >
%myents;
]>
<chapter id="plugin-loader">
  <title>
    Writing Plugins for the MIND Compiler
    </title>

  <para>
  The Mind Compiler supports a plugin infrastructure that allows third parties 
  to implement extensions without necessarily modifying the mainstream compiler.
  This chapter introduces this plugin infrastructure and explains how one write a new plugin.
  </para>

  <section id="ana-plugin">
    <title>Anatomy of a plugin</title>
	<para>
	A plugin is described in an XML manifest file, called mind-plugin.xml.
	 Currently, the MIND compiler doesn't support any
	specific control features for enabling or disabling plugins. It basically discovers all 
	manifest files called mind-plugin.xml residing in the class path and activates them
	in a non-specified order. Therefore, the user who wants to enable a plugin should set 
	the MIND_CLASSPATH environment variable so that the plugin is included in the classpath 
	of the compiler.
	</para>
	<para>
	The syntax of mind-plugin files is pretty simple. As illustrated in 
	<xref linkend="ex:basic-plugin"/>, the root tag, called plugin, 
	has two arguments. The argument called <code>id</code> assigns an identifier to the plugin. This identifier 
	must be unique amongst all plugins loaded by the compiler.
	The argument called <code>name</code> specifies the name of the plugin. 
	The <code>name</code> of a plugin can be any string literal including spaces.
	</para>
	
	<example id="ex:basic-plugin">
	<title>Description of a simple plugin.</title>
	<programlisting linenumbering="numbered" role="xml">
	<![CDATA[
	<plugin id="com.example.myPlugin" name="My Plugin">
	   <extension-point id="myNewExtensionPoint"/>
	   <extension point="org.ow2.mind.mindc.command-line-options">
	     ...
	   </extension>
	</plugin>
	]]>
	</programlisting>
	</example>
    
    <para>
    Plugins may define two types of elements: <emphasis>extension-points</emphasis> 
    and <emphasis>extensions</emphasis>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    Definition of extension points enables the implementation of plugins that are 
    extensible. That is, a plug-in may define an extension point which can be seen
    as a slot where extensions defined by other plugins may be plugged in to. Indeed,
    the MIND compiler itself is designed as a set of plugins which define the default
    extension-points which are hosted by the mainstream implementation. Those default 
    extension points are described in <xref linkend="def-ext"/>.
    </para>
    
    <para>
    The <code>extension-point</code> element has only one argument, its identifier
    (i.e. <code>id</code>). The <code>id</code> argument defines a name for the extension. Plugins 
    may define multiple extension points.
    Note that the <code>id</code> of an extension point specifies a local name which is unique inside the plugin. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
    The second type of element which may be found in a plugin description is <code>extension</code>.
    The <code>extension</code> element 
    has only one argument, namely <code>point</code>, which specifies the extension
    point where this extension will be plugged into. The value of the <code>point</code> 
    element must refer to the qualified name of an extension point which is
    obtained by the aggregation of the plugin id defining the extension point and the local
    name of the extension point. 
    </para>
    
    <para>
    Each extension point may have an internal syntax which is defined specifically
    for the requirements of the extension point. 
    Currently, no grammar definition language is supported for specifying such an
    internal syntax. That is, the programmer of an extension point may implement a
    DOM parser and document the internal syntax apart from the implementation code.
    </para>
 
  </section>
  
 

  <section id="def-ext">
    <title>Default Extension Points</title>

    <para>This section describes the extension points that are supported 
    by the mainstream MIND compiler. 
    </para>

    <section id="def-ext-cli">
      <title>Command Line Options</title>
      <para>One can add new command line options to the mindc launcher by defining extensions
      to the point called <code>org.ow2.mind.mindc.command-line-options</code>. There are
      different types of command options which are supported. <xref linkend="ex:cli"/> gives an example
      including an extension for each kind of options that are supported.</para>
      
      <example id="ex:cli">
        <title>Command-line option extensions</title>
        <programlisting  linenumbering="numbered" role="xml">
        <![CDATA[
<plugin id="com.examples.cli" name="Examples of command-line extensions.">
	<extension point="org.ow2.mind.mindc.command-line-options">
		<cmdFlag shortName="X" longName="FLAG"
			description="Description for cmdFlag"
			handler="org.ow2.mind.mindc.test.cli.CmdFlagHandler" />
	</extension>
	<extension point="org.ow2.mind.mindc.command-line-options">
		<cmdProperties shortName="Y" 
			description="Desc for cmdProperties"
			argNameDesc="argNameDesc"
			argValueDesc="argValueDesc"
			handler="org.ow2.mind.mindc.test.cli.CmdPropertiesHandler" />
	</extension>
	<extension point="org.ow2.mind.mindc.command-line-options">
		<cmdArgument shortName="Z" longName="cmdArgument"
			description="Desc for cmdArgument"
			arrgDesc="argDesc"
			deaultValue="defaultValue"
			allowMultiple="false"
			handler="org.ow2.mind.mindc.test.cli.CmdArgumentHandler" />	
	</extension>
	<extension point="org.ow2.mind.mindc.command-line-options">
		<cmdAppendOption shortName="W" longName="cmdAppendOption"
			description="Desc for cmdAppendOption"
			argNameDesc="argNameDesc"
			deaultValue="defaultValue"
			separator=";"
			handler="org.ow2.mind.mindc.test.cli.CmdAppendOptionHandler" />	
	</extension>
	<extension point="org.ow2.mind.mindc.command-line-options">
		<cmdPathOption shortName="Q" longName="cmdPathOption"
			description="Desc for cmdAppendOption"
			argDesc="argDesc"
			handler="org.ow2.mind.mindc.test.cli.CmdPathOptionHandler" />	
	</extension>
	
</plugin>
        ]]>
        </programlisting>
      </example>
      
      <para>
      Each command-line option extension must  provide an handler which will be invoked 
      if the option is found on the command line. Such handlers must implement the interface 
      depicted in <xref linkend="ex:cli-handler"/>.
      </para>
      
      	<example id="ex:cli-handler">
	<title>The CommandOptionHandler interface.</title>
	<programlisting linenumbering="numbered" role="java">
	<![CDATA[
public interface CommandOptionHandler {
  void processCommandOption(CmdOption cmdOption, Map<Object, Object> context)
      throws ADLException;
}
	]]>
	</programlisting>
	</example>
  
    </section>

	<section id="def-pa">
	  <title>Predefined annotations</title>
	  <para>
	  One can specify new predefined annotation packages, so that the annotations defined
	  in those packages are accessible with their local names. The extension point that is
	  defined for that purpose is called <code>org.ow2.mind.predefined-annotations</code>.
	  The <xref linkend="ex:pa"/> depicts an example for such an extension. 
	  </para>
      <example id="ex:pa">
	  <title>Definition of a new predefined annotation package.</title>
	  	<programlisting linenumbering="numbered" role="xml">
	<![CDATA[
  <extension point="org.ow2.mind.predefined-annotations">
  	<annotation package="com.examples.myAnnotations"/>
  </extension>
	]]>
	</programlisting>
	  </example>
	</section>

    <section id="def-cpl">
      <title>CPL parser</title>
  
      <para>It is possible to substitute the default CPL parser that is used by the MIND
      compiler. This can be pretty useful if the implementation of some extensions to the
      C programming language are needed. The <xref linkend="ex:cpl"/> depicts an example for such an extension. 
       </para>
       <example id="ex:cpl">
	  <title>Definition of a new predefined annotation package.</title>
	  	<programlisting linenumbering="numbered" role="xml">
	<![CDATA[
  <extension point="org.ow2.mind.preproc.cpl-parser">
    <factory class="com.examples.MyCPLPreprocessorFactory"/>
  </extension>
	]]>
	</programlisting>
	  </example>
      <para>
      Each CPL extension must provide a Factory class which will be used for instantiating the parser and lexer. 
      Such factory classes must implement the CPLPreprocessorFactory interface depicted in <xref linkend="ex:cpl-factory"/>. 
      </para>
      <example id="ex:cpl-factory">
	  <title>Definition of a new predefined annotation package.</title>
	  	<programlisting linenumbering="numbered" role="java">
	<![CDATA[
package org.ow2.mind.preproc;

public interface CPLPreprocessorFactory {
  Lexer getLexer(CharStream cs);

  Parser getParser(TokenStream ts);
}
	]]>
	</programlisting>
	  </example>
      
    </section>

    <section id="def-ext-back-def">
      <title>Definition Source Generators</title>
  
  	  <para>
  	  The extension point for adding new definition source generators is called 
  	  <code>org.ow2.mind.adl.definition-source-generators</code>.
  	  </para>
  
      <para>To be completed.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="def-ext-back-inst">
      <title>Instance Source Generators</title>
  
      <para>
  	  The extension point for adding new instance source generators is called 
  	  <code>org.ow2.mind.adl.instance-source-generators</code>.
  	  </para>
  
      <para>To be completed.</para>
    </section>

  </section>
</chapter>
